Today we start
with דף כט Daf Chaf-Tet today, but we start on כח עמוד
ב, Chaf-Chet Amud Bet, 28b, two dots near the top and actually,
you know, get into another very, thank you, a very large or
central conceptual question of the גמרא. Gemara. And I think now you're
starting to appreciate why חולין Chullin is such a like favorite מסכת
Masechet in certainly in the ישיבות Yeshivot because you have all of
these sort of broader conceptual questions that also that translate into other
fields. So for example, yesterday we had well we're going to have
the concept of majority is like the whole thing, we've referred to
it of course. Yesterday we had whether 50 percent is like the
majority, you know, we had in the beginning of the מסכת Masechet
questions about רוב Rov and חזקה Chazakah and so on. Here we
have a question about the how we conceptualize the act of שחיטה,
Shechitah, which in one way can also be a narrow question about
שחיטה, Shechitah, but it could also be generalized to other types of
questions which are things which are processes. And where how do we
sort of define a process. So let's take a look. It starts
on the two dots.
Okay, so here we go. רבי יהודה אומר
עד Rabbi Yehuda Omer Ad I'm sorry, no, am I on the
right place? I'm sorry, not כח עמוד ב, Chaf-Chet Amud Bet, כט
עמוד ב. Chaf-Tet Amud Bet. Excuse me, 29b. Okay, so...
Okay, I was wondering about that. So כט עמוד ב, Chaf-Tet Amud
Bet, let's take a look. Two dots near the top. אמר רבי
שמעון בן לקיש משום לוי. Amar Rabbi Shimon Ben Lakish mishum Levi.
So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said in the name of לוי סבא,
Levi Sava, Levi the elder. אינו לשחיטה אלא בסוף. Eno li-Shechitah ela
be-sof. שחיטה Shechitah occurs at the end of the process when you
know, get the two סימנים Simanim and the majority. That last cut
or the last two seconds which finishes the act, that's considered the
act of שחיטה. Shechitah. רבי יוחנן אמר ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף.
Rabbi Yochanan amar yeshno li-Shechitah mi-techilah ve-ad sof.
It's from the very beginning till the end. So again, this is
a very interesting question that you've got a process, process only finishes
at the end. Do you consider that from the very beginning you're
doing שחיטה Shechitah or do you say from the very beginning you're
doing the sort of preparatory stuff to the שחיטה Shechitah and the
שחיטה Shechitah is really only the very last thing that you've done.
Now logically of course you would say you're doing שחיטה Shechitah from
the beginning, especially because if you're not doing שחיטה Shechitah from the
beginning, you've already made the animal into a טריפה, treifa, right? So
certainly the logic is to say the whole process is called שחיטה.
Shechitah.
Right, the whole thing. It's a process not an act, meaning the
difference between a process and an act is that although here it
does take place very quickly, but anyway an act normally is like,
you know, you would say like one thing, a process has stages,
but even though it has stages, now here too you might say
it takes place in a second we'll call it an act not
a process, but even if we admit that we're calling it a
process, that there are stages to it and maybe stages that are
divided by milliseconds, but nevertheless you would still say that the entire
process is the process of שחיטה Shechitah even if it's only completed
at the end and especially as I said otherwise why is the
animal not a טריפה. treifa.
Interestingly, the גמרא Gemara says there's a פסול Pesul of שהייה. Shehiyah.
How are you going to
have if you're really not doing anything? Right, that's another good point.
Why is there a פסול Pesul of שהייה Shehiyah in the middle
if it's not considered the act of שחיטה Shechitah till the very
last thing? And these are great questions that the גמרא Gemara should
ask and does. You know, I mean the טריפה treifa question is
the most obvious. So then you have to like reframe it a
little and say okay, so this other stuff is considered like the
the you know the lead up till שחיטה Shechitah or the process
of שחיטה Shechitah but somehow the act of שחיטה Shechitah is until
the end. This position that it's all at the end is a
definitely a very difficult one because you're forced to give some significance
to what preceded. Let's take a look at...
It's like שכר, Sachar, right?
יש שכר... Yesh Sachar... yes, that's a good point too, although there
it's easier, right? Michael's question is when somebody rents a house are
they חייב chayav for every minute that they're there to pay that
proportion of the rent, or is the obligation of rent only come
at the end of the month, you know, and until then there's
no obligation yet to pay. So there's these types of questions obviously
they can based on the case they either make more or less
sense and can be conceptualized, you know, differently, right? One might be
more of a contract question, this is more of a defining a
process question, but these are you know central types of these are
central types of conceptual questions that the גמרא Gemara asks. So let's
take a look at how where it goes from this. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says, הכל מודים היכא דשחט סימן אחד
עובד כוכבים וסימן אחד ישראל שהיא פסולה. Ha-kol modim heicha di-shachat siman
echad oved kochavim ve-siman echad Yisrael she-hi pesulah.
Everybody would agree if a non-Jew slaughtered the first סימן siman and
the Jew the second one that it's invalid, even if you say
the שחיטה Shechitah is only at the end. Why? שהרי נעשה בה
מעשה טריפה ביד עובד כוכבים. She-harei na-asah ba-ma-aseh treifa be-yad oved kochavim.
Because even because okay, when the non-Jew is done the animal is
already a טריפה, treifa, right? It already has one סימן siman cut.
So even if you say the act of שחיטה Shechitah is only
at the end, you don't have to invalidate this because the non-Jew
did an act of שחיטה, Shechitah, it doesn't matter, by the time
the Jew shows up the animal's already a טריפה. treifa. So that
everybody would agree is invalid. ועולת העוף נמי, Ve-olas ha-of nami,
by an עולה olah bird which you have to cut both סימנים,
simanim, היכא דמלק סימן אחד למטה וסימן אחד למעלה. Heicha di-malak siman
echad lemata ve-siman echad lemala. If you did one סימן siman at
the bottom of the altar and one at the top and an
עולה olah bird is only at the top of the altar, nobody
would say oh well you know it's not a problem what you
did at the bottom of the altar because that's not yet the
שחיטה Shechitah act. Meaning it's just trying to understand what are the
relevances of this. So it says a non-Jew doing it first... It's
definitely a problem even if you don't call it a שחיטה shechitah
act, the animal's already a טריפה. tereifah. But a bird עולה Olah
doing one סימן siman at the bottom, well why don't we say,
oh, if שחיטה shechitah is only at the end, you haven't yet
done a שחיטה shechitah to the bird עולה, Olah, so you haven't
done it in the wrong place because what you did at the
bottom wasn't considered a שחיטה? shechitah? No, that's also not going to
get you off. Why?
So everybody would still say פסולה, psulah, it's invalid, what you did
at the bottom, it was an עולה Olah done at the bottom,
the first סימן, siman, why? שעשה בה מעשה חטאת העוף למטה. she'asah
bah ma'aseh chatas of lemata. Because at least what you did do
is cutting one סימן siman is significant for a bird חטאת. chatas.
And the problem of doing a bird עולה Olah at the bottom
of the altar is that you're treating it like a חטאת. chatas.
So since at the bottom of the altar you cut one סימן,
siman, so you've treated it like a חטאת chatas in that you've
cut one סימן, siman, which would have made it good for a
חטאת, chatas, and you did it at the bottom of the altar,
which is what you would have done for a חטאת. chatas. Everybody
agrees that you invalidated it by doing the חטאת chatas act at
the bottom, even though before ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish position, you have
not yet done שחיטה. shechitah. שחיטה shechitah is only at the end.
Okay, so we're sort of like eliminating cases which are certainly a
problem regardless, even if you only put שחיטה shechitah at the end.
So where does it matter that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish puts שחיטה
shechitah at the end and not in terms of the whole process?
אלא, Ella, here's where it matters. לא נחלקו אלא כגון ששחט סימן
אחד בחוץ וסימן אחד בפנים. lo necheleku ela kigon sheshachat siman echad
bechutz v'siman echad bifnim. You שחט shechted one סימן siman of a
קרבן korban outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You had a
cow, one סימן siman you שחט shechted outside and the final סימן
siman you שחט shechted inside, somehow without doing שהייה. shehiyah. But okay,
let's say you were one step out of the עזרה, azarah, you
had your קרבן, korban, you were in the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim,
you got too impatient, you started שחיטה shechting it outside and you
finished שחיטה shechting it inside. Now, a קרבן korban שחט shechted outside
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're חייב chayav for שוחטי חוץ. shochtei
chutz. Right? You have to bring your קרבנות korbanos to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Have you שחט shechted a קרבן korban outside of
the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? You only שחט shechted one סימן. siman.
So if you say the process begins at the beginning, you did
a שחיטה shechitah act at the beginning. If you say it only
comes at the end, so then you have not yet done a
שחיטה shechitah act. So let's take a look. So, דאמר, d'amar, so
it says like this, למאן דאמר leman d'amar according to the one
who says,
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshno l'shechitah mitichilah ve'ad sof, that the
שחיטה shechitah process starts from the beginning till the end, מחייב, mechayiv,
you're חייב chayav because you שחט shechted it outside, you did a
שחיטה shechitah act, not maybe the whole שחיטה shechitah act, but at
least you began the שחיטה shechitah act already.
ולמאן דאמר אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף, u'leman d'amar eino l'shechitah ela be'sof,
it's only at the end, לא מחייב, lo mechayiv, you're not חייב.
chayav. Now, this by the way, might give us an opportunity to,
you know, tone down the position that it's all at the end
because as we said, it's really crazy to say until then you
haven't done anything, the whole act comes at the end, you know,
why did you not make it a טריפה, tereifah, why are there
the פסולים? psulim? So maybe what it means is yes the... what?
Well okay, so maybe A, it's just to be מחמיר machmir on
you the question, how are we going to be מחמיר machmir at
the beginning? And another way of framing are we going to be
מחמיר machmir at the beginning is that the question is, if I
when I'm beginning it, do how do I describe it? Do I
say I am in the process of שחיטה, shechting, right, which means
it's incomplete, I can't say that I've done שחיטה shechitah yet, I'm
in the process of שחיטה shechting but it's still incomplete, right? Or
do I say no, you know, I have done a
שחיטה? shechitah?
Right. So what?
So no, when you have שחט shechted let's say one סימן, siman,
how would you describe it? If you say אינה לשחיטה אלא בסוף,
eino l'shechitah ela be'sof, it doesn't mean until then it's nothing. It
may be mean you haven't yet done a שחיטה, shechitah, you're in
the process of שחיטה shechting but you haven't yet finished the שחיטה,
shechitah, the שחיטה's shechitah only when it's done. Whereas the other one
says no, even when, even at any intermediate stage, you can already
say I've done a שחיטה. shechitah. Okay? So that now explains... A,
that certainly makes the first position a lot more understandable at the
expense of making the second one less understandable, but it also explains
what they're debating. If I שחט shechted one סימן siman outside and
one סימן siman inside, if all I say is I'm in the
process of שחיטה, shechting, okay, but you haven't yet שחט shechted a
קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you just were, you
had begun a process of שחיטה, shechting, right? But if I say
no, no, no, that actually by שחיטה shechting one סימן siman I've
already שחט, shechted, so then you שחט shechted a קרבן korban outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So that's another way of understanding the
debate. Yes?
How could you compare this to a surgeon starting surgery and not...
You can compare it to any process. Yeah, you can compare it
to any process.
I mean, when the knife goes into a body, right, is is
that, can he say...
Right, I am in the process of surgery, right, but
you're not done surgery until it's complete.
Well right, so that's the funny thing is that you know you
would sort of say well, okay, if that's the question then isn't
the first position obvious? You're in the process of doing surgery or
in the process of doing שחיטה shechitah from the beginning, but you
haven't done, finished your שחיטה shechitah till the end. Right, so that's
you know, so again, if you explain one position better, the other
one becomes a little bit less harder to understand. But let's work
with this explanation now because it does help understanding how you could
say it's at the end and still have all of make it
okay, you know, all the criteria beforehand and it's not a טריפה
tereifah before... Yes, of course you're in the process of שחיטה... shechting...
But when do we call the act a שחיטה shechita act? Are
we prepared to call it a שחיטה shechita act in the middle,
or are we prepared to call it a process until you've finished?
So yes.
So usually intent,
intent seems to be completely irrelevant here, although we
will say in a minute, you know not a minute, in a
day or two, we'll repeat the idea that שחיטה shechita does not
require intent. But the גמרא Gemara does not seem to factor that
into this question.
It assumes that in all these cases they're trying to do שחיטה,
shechita, you know, or it's not relevant what you're trying to do,
that the question is still how do we define, you know, how
do we define it in the middle of this process.
How he brings it inside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What? When
he slaughtered outside?
Yeah, so you were one step out, you were in the עזרת
נשים, Ezras Nashim, you were one step out from the line, you
slaughtered it, it took one step in and you finished slaughtering.
Oh, he was at the door.
Yeah, you'd have to explain the scenario. The גמרא Gemara doesn't really
care about the scenario, but that's what you're asking. Why? Okay. שהייה
Shehiyah is pausing. Okay. All right, so let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this. Okay, so all right, all right, so let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
למאן דאמר ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, Leman damar yeshno leshchita mitechila
ve’ad sof, if שחיטה shechita is from the beginning to the end,
מחייב, mechayiv, you’re מחייב mechayiv because you slaughtered it outside even one
סימן. siman. למאן דאמר אינו לשחיטה אלא בסוף, Leman damar eino leshchita
ela besof, no, שחיטה shechita is only at the end, לא מחייב,
lo mechayiv, you’re not מחייב. mechayiv. So אמר ליה רבא בר שימי,
Amar lei Rava bar Shimi, so רבא בר שימי Rava bar Shimi
said, מר לא אמר הכי, Mar lo amar hachi, the master didn't
say this. Who's the master? ומנו רב יוסף, Umanu Rav Yosef, רב
יוסף. Rav Yosef. So what did רב יוסף Rav Yosef say?
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said you can't frame the debate that way.
Why? היכא דשחט סימן אחד בחוץ וסימן אחד בפנים, Heicha deshachat siman
echad bachutz vesiman echad bifnim, if that’s the way you want to
frame the certain the case that you’re looking at, one סימן siman
outside, נמי פסול, nami pasul, everybody would say it’s invalid even if
you say that שחיטה’s shechita at the end. Why? שהרי עשה בה
מעשה חטאת העוף בחוץ, Sheharei asa bah ma’aseh chatas ha’of bachutz, because
cutting one סימן siman is an act of a קרבן korban act
by a bird חטאת. chatas. So remember, the transgress the transgression is
slaughtering a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef just has a slight little qualifier. He would say
whatever you say in general,
everybody would agree a person transgresses slaughtering a קרבן korban outside the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as soon as you slaughter one סימן, siman,
because there’s one type of a קרבן korban that is valid with
one סימן, siman, and what is that? A bird
חטאת. chatas. So רש"י Rashi tries to say we're talking about birds,
תוספות Tosafos says no no no, he’s just making an analogy. But
whatever it is, look, we don’t have to focus on this, this
is just a parenthetical point that he is saying that when it
comes to the prohibition of slaughtering קרבנות korbanos outside the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, as soon as you do an act that would count
for any one קרבן, korban, even if it is just the slaughtering
of a bird חטאת chatas which is one סימן, siman, that’s enough
to have been the transgression. Okay, so he just wants to put
that case off limits. Okay, because that is an act of a
חטאת העוף chatas ha’of למטה. lemata. לא נחלקו, Lo nechelku,
so if you want to say the debate is by slaughtering outside
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, here’s how to frame it. לא נחלקו
אלא ela כגון ששחט,
I’m sorry did I do that again? No,
where were we? לא מחייב, lo mechayiv, אמר ליה רבא בר שימי
לא אמר הכי, amar lei Rava bar Shimi lo amar hachi, שהרי
עשה בה מעשה חטאת העוף בחוץ. sheharei asa bah ma’aseh chatas ha’of
bachutz. לא נחלקו אלא כגון ששחט מיעוט סימנין בחוץ וגמרו בפנים. Lo
nechelku ela kegon sheshachat miyut simanin bachutz ugmaro bifnim. So here would
be the case: you slaughtered the first 30% of the trachea or
whatever it was outside, and then you did, right, the remainder of
everything inside. So it’s the same idea except you didn’t do a
full סימן. siman. Full סימן siman everybody would say you’re מחייב. mechayiv.
You did a quarter of a סימן. siman. So if you say
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshno leshchita mitechila ve’ad sof,
it doesn't matter, you don't even have to do a full סימן,
siman, from the very moment you begin you're doing שחיטה shechita and
you did שחיטה shechita outside. Whereas if you say אינו לשחיטה אלא
בסוף, eino leshchita ela besof, no, you only have right where we're
saying now, might have began begun the process but you did not
yet do שחיטה shechita and therefore you're not מחייב. mechayiv. למאן דאמר
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף מחייב, Leman damar yeshno leshchita mitechila ve’ad
sof mechayiv, so if it starts from the beginning you’re מחייב. mechayiv.
למאן דאמר אינו לשחיטה אלא בסוף, Leman damar eino leshchita ela besof,
if it’s only at the end, לא מחייב, mechayiv. you’re not מחייב.
Okay, so now we have that debate and again maybe the question
is do you consider it having begun the process of שחיטה shechita
or, you know, in the middle of slaughtering or having done שחיטה.
shechita. So מתיבי רבי זירא, Maseivi Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
asked: here we have a משנה Mishnah by פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah.
כל העוסקין בפרה, Kol ha’oskin baparah, right, the תורה Torah says that
anybody who involves themselves in the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah becomes טמא.
tamei. So מתחילה ועד סוף, mitechila ve’ad sof, from the beginning of
the process, the first act that is done to a פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah is that it is שחט, shachat, before that it's all
clearly all just considered preparatory. The first ritual act is the שחיטה.
shechita. So from the beginning of the ritual, from the beginning of
the שחיטה shechita till you're done, anybody that involves themselves in the
process מטמא בגדים, metamei vegadim, becomes טמא tamei and it's a strong
טומאה tumah so it even causes their clothes to become טמא tamei
that they're wearing. Okay, now there's another הלכה halacha about from the
very beginning of the process. ופוסלין אותם במלאכה אחרת. Uposlin osam bimelacha
acheres. There's a הלכה halacha that when you are doing any of
the מלאכה melacha of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, if you're in
the middle of doing another מלאכה melacha at the same time, you
invalidate it. So let's say there I am, I am, I don't
know, you know, putting the water on the ashes of the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah and while I'm doing that I'm also like tying
my shoe or something. Okay, so I've now invalidated it. The הלכה
halacha is that if you're doing any other מלאכה melacha at the
same time of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, you invalidate the ashes
of the פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah. Does במלאכה bimelacha mean anything?
No, anything.
Any other type of activity. Okay, exactly what the parameters are I'm
not sure, like if scratching your head is considered a מלאכה, melacha,
probably not. Okay, but some other type of act. Okay, so now
those are the two things that apply. So let's see where this
goes from this. Now,
ופוסל אותן במלאכה אחרת. uposeil otan bimelacha acheret. עירבה ופסלה בשחיטתה, iruva
ufaslu bishchitata, בין קודם פסולה בין לאחר פסולה. bein kodem psula bein
l'achar psula. Now, let's say we're going to bracket the whole מלאכה
melacha issue for now. That's not directly our interest. Okay, now,
let's say געזונטהייט. gezundheit.
Let's say while you're working on the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, some
invalidity occurs to it. What invalidity occurs to it? רשי Rashi says
let's say, for example, you did the שחיטה shechita incorrectly and you
made it a נבילה. neveilah. Or תוספות Tosafot says let's say exactly
the invalidity we mentioned a second ago, you did another מלאכה melacha
at the same time. Okay, but something occurred that invalidated it. So
now here's the question: You're doing something with the פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah, you're burning it, you're שוחט shechting it, whatever. Something occurred to
invalidate it. Do I become טמא? tamei? The right, it's not yet
going to be completed, its ashes of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah became
invalid in the middle. But when I was dealing with it, I
was involving myself whatever I was doing, burning it, שוחט shechting it,
whatever, it had not yet become טמא tamei when I started, invalid
when I started. So do I become טמא? tamei? because I was
doing one of the processes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah before
the invalidity occurred. So let's take a look.
Okay, עירבה ופסלה בשחיטתה, iruva ufaslu bishchitata, some invalidity occurred during the
שחיטה. shechita. Again, either it means you made it a נבילה, neveilah,
you messed up the שחיטה, shechita, or you did another מלאכה melacha
at the same time. בין קודם פסולה בין לאחר פסולה, bein kodem
psula bein l'achar psula, whether the invalidity occurred before you were שוחט
shechting it and involved in it before the invalidity or after the
invalidity. בין קודם פסולה בין לאחר פסולה, bein kodem psula bein l'achar
psula, אינם מטמא בגדים. einam mitamei bgadim. Okay, your clothes do not
become טמא. tamei. Why? Because the assumption is if the שחיטה shechita
is ruined, so there was never a שחיטה. shechita. If there was
never a שחיטה, shechita, it never got started. If it never got
started, whatever you were doing, you weren't doing with the process of
a פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. The process didn't start yet if you
don't have a good שחיטה. shechita. However,
בהזאתה, behaza'atah, if an invalidity occurred at the sprinkling, now this is
not the sprinkling of the ashes, it's the sprinkling of the blood.
We're still preparing the ashes, you're sprinkling the blood. So in that
type of a case, קודם פסולה, kodem psula, if you were involved
in it before the invalidity of the blood sprinkling at the blood
sprinkling time, מטמא בגדים. mitamei bgadim. Your clothes are טמא tamei because
you were involved in it when it was still valid. לאחר פסולה,
l'achar psula, if you were involved in it after the invalidity occurred
by the blood sprinkling, אינם מטמא בגדים. einam mitamei bgadim. Your clothes
are not טמא, tamei, you are not טמא tamei because when you
were involved in it it is not טמא.
tamei. Wait, mean בהזאתה behaza'atah messed up, the guy who just did
the שחיטה shechita is still טמא. tamei.
Right, or if there are two people involved in the הזאה, haza'ah,
you did the first three sprinklings and I did the next four,
and you had an invalidity, what I will do is not a
problem, what you did is a problem because you were involved in
it before it became פסול. pasul. So the simple
point is, if you're involved in it before it's פסול, pasul, you're
טמא, tamei, after it's פסול pasul you're not טמא. tamei. But if
it became פסול pasul during שחיטה, shechita, nobody is טמא tamei because
then there was never a good שחיטה, shechita, it never got off
the ground. Okay, and you can sort of probably anticipate what the
גמרא's Gemara question is. Because if you say שחיטה shechita begins at
the beginning, so why do we say that there was no, you
know, you never got off the ground? You got a question David?
Background. Anybody come in contact with
a נבילה? neveilah?
Yes, but with a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah it's not just contact,
it's being involved in the like מלאכה melacha of doing the פרה
אדומה. Parah Adumah. So even if you manage involved yourself in it
without actually, you know, touching it.
So שוחט shocheit who goes through שוחט shechting chickens? Right, as an
eighty percent, ninety percent, ninety-five percent has one that's that
doesn't work.
They're טמא. tamei. Right.
But it's a light טומאה, tumah, you go to the מקווה mikvah
you're טהור, tahor, no sprinkling of ashes of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
and so on, you know, no big consequences
about like where you're excluded from. I mean yes, you are טמא,
tamei, you can't eat קרבנות, korbanot, you can't eat תרומה, terumah, but
fine, you go to the מקווה, mikvah, you know, so it's not
a huge consequence of that טומאה. tumah. The one that has the
big consequences are things that relate to humans, dead bodies,
זב, zav, זבה, zavah, מצורע, metzora, those are the ones.
So the question the גמרא Gemara is asking here is retrospective definition
of the process.
Yes, I definitely think it is. The problem question is, is that
how do you frame the two sides? Meaning if the question is
when does the process begin, it seems obvious that everybody would say
the process begins from the beginning. If the question is when have
you completed it, when have you done שחיטה, shechita, not just been
involved in the process, presumably that's at the end. So, you know,
either you can explain one well but at the expense of the
other. If we're trying to explain when are you done, so obviously
you're done at the end. If you're trying to explain when the
process began, obviously the process begins at the beginning. So, you know,
the question is how do you understand the other opinion based on
how you frame. the question is how do you understand the other
opinion based on how you frame the question? It's hard to see
where there's a gray area here.
So if the process begins at the beginning, you have a number
of people involved in the process. Right. But if you execute your
section effectively and then you're gone. Yeah, then you wouldn't become טמא.
tamei.
No, you are טמא. tamei. Any part of the process you involve
yourself in, you're טמא. tamei.
This is
by the פרה, parah, by
the way.
פרה אדומה. Parah adumah. We're talking about פרה אדומה. Parah adumah. We've
shifted now. We're not talking about normal שחיטה. shechita. We're talking about
פרה. parah. Right. Right.
So if the process is fully completed successfully,
right, at the very end, so
people who were who were involved in the whole thing, right, the
guy in the beginning who leaves the process is טמא.
tamei. That's the point of the פרה אדומה. Parah adumah. Is טמא.
tamei.
Is טמא. tamei.
Right, so that's an interesting, by the way, analogy. On the one
hand we're asking ourselves questions about the process of שחיטה, shechita, but
what we do find out is by the פרה אדומה Parah adumah
it's very clear that any stage of the process is relevant for
making you טמא. tamei. That is correct. So by the פרה אדומה
Parah adumah clearly the whole process, the focus on the process starts
at the beginning. That is correct. But still we're asking the שחיטה
shechita question of a normal case. Okay, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so it says like this: ואי אמרת,
Ve'ei amart, if you said יש לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yesh lishchita
mit'chila ve'ad sof, that the process of שחיטה shechita begins from the
beginning, or the act of שחיטה, shechita, וליפלוג נמי בשחיטתה, v'liflog nami
bishchitato, why do you only say that by שחיטה shechita whenever the
פסול pasul occurs,
you know, everybody is טהור tahor because the process didn't begin. Why
do you say that? Why don't you say אי אירע הפסול בשחיטה
קודם פסול מטמא בגדים, iy ira'a hap'sul bishchita kodem p'sul meta'amei begadim,
if there was some problem that occurred during the שחיטה, shechita, if
you were involved before the פסול, pasul, you are טמא tamei because
the process began from the beginning. ולאחר פסול, Ve'achar p'sul, if you
were involved after the invalidity, אינו מטמא בגדים, eino meta'amei begadim, you're
not טמא. tamei.
Is it only one person anyway?
No, it could be different people or whatever. That yeah, that's the
only way we're having a discussion in שחיטה. shechita. Yeah,
we like, like the גמרא Gemara discusses by the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, I do one סימן siman and
you do the other, whatever it is. Okay, so anyway the גמרא
Gemara says, although the גמרא Gemara will touch back on that in
a minute. Anyway, so you see that it assumes that if there's
a problem during שחיטה shechita everybody's off the hook. Sounds like שחיטה
shechita is not considered to be a שחיטה shechita until the end.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבא, Amar Rava, no, so רבא
Rava says one minute. נתקלקלה שחיטה קאמרת? Niskalkela shechita ka'amart? If the
שחיטה shechita got ruined, that's what you're talking about? Ha! That's not
a problem. שאני התם, Shani hatam, there it's different. דאיגלאי מילתא למפרע,
D'igla milta le'mafrea, retroactively it has been revealed דלאו שחיטה היא כלל,
d'lav shechita hi klal, that you never did a שחיטה. shechita. So
here's an important qualifier. Even the one that says the process begins
at the beginning, that's assuming it ends well. If the process, if
you begin a process of שחיטה shechita and then in the end
you make it a נבילה, neveilah, retroactively you were never doing the
שחיטה. shechita. So when you, so once it ended with a good
שחיטה, shechita, then we can say it began at the beginning. But
when you mess it up, then we said you've never did a
שחיטה shechita even from the first minute. Okay, which makes a lot
of sense. תוספות Tosafos goes a little bit more out on a
limb, because remember תוספות Tosafos said the problem here by the פרה,
parah, by the שחיטה, shechita, wasn't you made it a נבילה, neveilah,
wasn't you ruined the שחיטה, shechita, it was that you did some
מלאכה. melachah. So according to תוספות, Tosafos, right, which is not, the
שחיטה shechita was still a good שחיטה, shechita, it's just you did
a מלאכה. melachah. So תוספות Tosafos has to say, Oh, but even
so what we would say is, since in the end it wasn't
a שחיטת פרה אדומה, shechitas parah adumah, right, it wasn't a good
שחיטת פרה אדומה shechitas parah adumah because that wasn't done correctly, then
we can never say the process of פרה אדומה Parah adumah began.
For תוספות Tosafos it's a little bit more, it's a little more
sort of nuanced. But for רש"י Rashi the point is a very
simple one. We can even the one who says it begins at
the beginning assumes it's ending correctly. Okay, yes.
You view פרה אדומה parah adumah as a perfect, is the way
that absolutely the most perfect way of doing שחיטה shechita and applying
to daily life and whatever?
No, פרה
אדומה
parah
adumah is one example where שחיטה shechita is important, but there it's
there it's a clear example where we can say we want to
know at an earlier stage in the שחיטה shechita was it considered
that you were doing שחיטה shechita yet.
Can you rectify theoretically?
And now the גמרא Gemara said, yes, you could say you were
doing שחיטה shechita at the beginning stages assuming it ended correctly. Our
scenario was when it did not end correctly. Yeah.
It's safe to, and that was with the idea of surgery, if
there was a blackout in the hospital and the generator wasn't working
and the surgery wasn't complete, you had not from,
right, right, we weren't doing surgery from the beginning. Although I don't
know, you know, I mean it's interesting what people would say. If
you know, what do they say, you know, the surgery was a
success but the patient died, right? So you could say that something
you, you know, you ruined it at the end, but you know
but there also because each stage, surgery constitutes a lot of separate
acts, right? There's the cutting the patient open, there's the doing this,
the doing that. So would we actually say there that if it
didn't, if you ruined something at the end you weren't doing surgery
in the beginning? That maybe not. But here clearly it is an
integrated process, you know it's one single process. So if it doesn't
end by being successful, everybody's going to agree we don't say you
start that it was a process of שחיטה. shechita. It may have
been an attempt at שחיטה shechita but it wasn't a process of
שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so let's keep on going.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, I'm sorry, skipped the line. Okay.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אי קשיא לי הא קשיא לי, ee kashya
li, ha kashya li, if I've got a question about this whole
debate here's my question. למאן דאמר אין לשחיטה אלא בסוף, Leman de'amar
ein lishchita ela besof, according to the one who says there is
no שחיטה shechita except at the end. says that שחיטה shchitah is
at the end. לפלוג בהכשירה דפרה. liflog b'cheshora d'para.
So even assuming that the פרה para was a kosher פרה, para,
right, you could have- געזונטהייט- gezundheit you could have used
a normal example of not any פסול, psul, the פרה אדומה para
aduma being done correctly, and still distinguish between when somebody becomes טמא.
tamei. What would be the example? כגון ששחטוה בתרי גברי, k'gon sheshachtua
bitrei gavrei, two people shechted it, there you go Michael. גברא קמא
לא מיטמא וגברא בתרא מיטמא. gavrah kama lo mitamei v'gavrah batra mitamei.
Let's say one guy did a- one סימן, siman, and the other
guy did the second סימן. siman. So we would say- without there
being any שהייה? shehiya? Without there being any שהייה, shehiya, yeah. Halachically
I know although we heard yesterday about even the tiniest second, halachically
שהייה shehiya means the time it takes to- to do a whole
שחיטה. shchitah. So it's possible. Okay, or they had two knives and
they were getting ready at different points within the פרה אדומה, para
aduma, you could ima- whatever it is. Anyway, so the first guy
hasn't yet done שחיטה, shchitah, he's not טמא, tamei, only if the
second guy has done שחיטה, shchitah, forget a פסול. psul. Why not
just talk about what moment during the process somebody becomes טמא? tamei?
And if it's only at the end of שחיטה, shchitah, then only
the person who would be doing the end of שחיטה shchitah would
be טמא. tamei. Okay, so אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, so
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, תרי גברי בחד זבחה קאמרת, trei gavrei
b'chad zivcha kamarta, one minute, two people with one sacrifice? בא מיני
דהא, ba minei d'ha, forget that case. דתנינא detanina we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, T, and we taught this yesterday, תזבח, tizbach, it
says you shall slaughter it by a sacrifice, שלא יהיו שנים שוחטין
זבח אחד. shelo yehyu shnayim shochtin zevach echad. Only one person, not
two people, it's in the singular, now really it's in the plural,
but we're reading it in a singular, okay? תזבחהו, tizbachuhu, you shall
slaughter it, שלא יהא אחד שוחט שני זבחים. shelo yehei echad shochet
shnei zevachim. One person should not slaughter two sacrifices at the same
time. Now of course the problem is is that the verse is
תזבחהו, tizbachuhu, you plural should slaughter it. So אמר רב כהנא, Amar
Rav Kahana, תזבחהו tizbachuhu כתיב. ketiv. So we're going to read it
without the ו, vav, so it means you singular should slaughter it.
So by sacrifices only one person slaughtering one sacrifice. Don't slaughter two
at the same time, don't have two people slaughtering. And because פרה
אדומה para aduma is a quasi-sacrifice, all full in issue the גמרא
Gemara constantly returns to, the quasi-sacrifice status of a פרה אדומה, para
aduma, right, it is out of the temple, but it is called
a חטאת, chatas, so therefore we can't have a scenario of one-
two people slaughtering the פרה אדומה. para aduma. So the scenario- right.
Okay, so the scenario is impossible. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye,
so אביי Abaye said, לאו איתמר עלה, lav itmar alah, one minute,
it was said about it, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו דברי רבי
אליעזר ברבי שמעון zo divrei Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon סתימאה. stimah. This
idea that two- two people cannot slaughter sacrifice, that's the opinion of
רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon who is like the
סתם stam author of that משנה. Mishnah. אבל, aval, top of ל"ח
עמוד א, lamed-ches amud aleph, אבל חכמים אומרים, aval chachamim omrim, but
the חכמים chachamim say, שנים שוחטין זבח אחד, shnayim shochtin zevach echad,
two people can slaughter one sacrifice. And therefore according to the חכמים,
chachamim, your question is still legitimate. Why not give that scenario? And
גמרא Gemara says I'll even give you a better case. ולרבי אליעזר
ברבי שמעון נמי, u'l'Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon nami, even according to רבי
אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon I can give you a
scenario by פרה אדומה para aduma where I want to know beginning
or end, when is it considered the process, when does טומאה tumah
occur? What's the scenario? נמי לפלוג כגון ששחט חד גברא בשני סודרין.
nami liflog k'gon sheshachat chad gavrah bishnei sudarin. One person was wearing
two handkerchiefs. Now they sort of wore even the men at those
time wore a handkerchief. So basically here I am, I'm shchting, I
start with a certain handkerchief on my head, let's say a כיפה,
kippah, I start, my כיפה kippah falls down in the middle, and
somebody comes and puts another כיפה kippah on my head while I'm
up to the second סימן, siman, right? Now remember פרה אדומה para
aduma causes me to become טמא tamei and my clothes to become
טמא. tamei. So here's the question: did my first כיפה kippah become
טמא? tamei?
Because only- my first כיפה kippah was only on me at the
beginning of the process and not at the end. So I don't
need to introduce another גברא, gavrah, I just need to introduce another
piece of clothing. Okay, so that's the question. בשני סודרין. bishnei sudarin.
דסודר קמא לא מיטמא, dsudar kama lo mitama, if שחיטה's shchitah only
at the end, then the first handkerchief, in my scenario's the כיפה,
kippah, would not become טמא, tamei, וסודר בתרא מיטמא, v'sudar batra mitama,
only the last one. So why didn't he give that scenario? If
the, you know, if it's true that שחיטה's shchitah only at the
end, it could have given that scenario to describe to emphasize that
the טומאה tumah only comes at the end. So גמרא Gemara says,
"Alright, you know what, you're right. It could have if it wanted
to talk about that." אלא בפסולה דפרה קא מיירי בהכשירה לא קא
מיירי. ela b'psula d'para kama'iri d'cheshora lo kama'iri. This משנה Mishnah was
interested in talking about when the process became invalid, right, did the
invalidity come, you know, did the טומאה tumah come before the invalidity
or after the invalidity? It was talking about scenarios where the פרה
para process was invalidated. It wasn't talking about scenarios where everything was
done correctly and discussing like, you know, which clothes you were wearing.
So in theory you're right, but that wasn't the structure, that wasn't
the focus of the משנה.
Mishnah. מכל מקום מיהו, mikatzeh mihu, right?
Meaning if the שחיטה shchitah is- but you're right, if if שחיטה
shchitah was from beginning to end, then your first כיפה kippah would
be טמא. tamei. If שחיטה shchitah was only at the end, only
your second כיפה kippah would be טמא. tamei. Okay, yes, you're correct,
but that wasn't the interest of the משנה Mishnah to discuss that
scenario. Okay, so now we have had two נפקא מינות nafka minas
about this יש לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yesh l'shchitah mitichilah v'ad sof.
שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, you're shchting a קרבן korban outside the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the process begins there, and פרה אדומה, para aduma,
when does the process of the שחיטה shchitah begin? Okay, let's go.
Let's take a look at what else the גמרא gemara introduces into
this debate.
Are you going to answer his questions?
No. We're going to leave it as a debate. Okay. מתיב אבידי
בר אבין. Maysiv Avidi bar Avin. אבידי בר אבין Avidi bar Avin
asks from the following. ובמועד לשמו פטור שלא לשמו חייב. Uvemoed lishmo
patur shelo lishmo chayav. This is a קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Everybody
will remember from way back when in זבחים Zevachim that a קרבן
פסח korban pesach
that is שחט shechted as a non during the rest of the
year is considered a שלמים, shlamim, not a קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Okay. Now, there's another הלכה halacha which is that
if you שחט, shecht, the Torah says לא תשחט על חמץ דם
זבחי. Lo sishchat al chameitz dam zivchi. Do not שחט shecht my
sacrifice over
חמץ. chameitz. So חז"ל Chazal understand, or at least there's an opinion
that understands that's not only referring to שחיטת shechting the קרבן פסח
korban pesach when you have חמץ chametz in your house, but it's
to bringing any קרבן korban over the holiday of חג המצות Chag
Hamatzos when there is פסח, pesach, when there is חמץ chametz in
your house. So if you שחט shecht any קרבן korban while you
have חמץ chametz over פסח, pesach, you have transgressed לא תשחט על
חמץ דם זבחי, Lo sishchat al chameitz dam zivchi, because notice it
says my sacrifice in the generic and does not emphasize the קרבן
פסח. korban pesach. Okay. So here's a scenario: you have your sheep
that you were going to bring for a קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Somehow what's happened? It got lost. You brought another one. It's left
over. It's now the middle, it's now the third day of פסח.
Pesach. And you've got this sheep. You bring it to the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you slaughter it.
Have you transgressed slaughtering a sheep over, slaughtering a קרבן korban over
חמץ? chametz? Well, one of the other things you required in order
to transgress is that it be a valid קרבן. korban. So the
question of whether you have transgressed boils down to, right, is this
פסח pesach being brought now in the middle of פסח, Pesach, not
on the fourteenth of Nisan, when you שחט shecht it, is it
a valid קרבן korban or not? Okay. Now, normally we assume a
פסח pesach when it's not the fourteenth of Nisan is a שלמים
shlamim and it is a valid קרבן. korban. So let's take a
look though, because if you called it a פסח pesach at the
wrong time, it wouldn't be valid. But if you call it a
שלמים, shlamim, it is valid, right? So let's take a look at
what we say about this. ובמועד, Uvemoed, on the יום טוב Yom
Tov itself, on חג המצות, Chag Hamatzos, right, חול המועד פסח, Chol
Hamoed Pesach, לשמו פטור. lishmo patur. If you slaughter it as a
קרבן פסח, korban pesach, then you're exempt. It's an invalid sacrifice and
you're exempt from bringing a sacrifice with חמץ. chametz. שלא לשמו, Shelo
lishmo, if you slaughtered it not as a קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
as a שלמים, shlamim, then it is a valid sacrifice and then
חייב, chayav, you have transgressed.
Legal definition or just intent?
This here's intent. לשמו ושלא לשמו, lishmo veshelo lishmo, that's a question
of intent. The problem that's not addressed here is: what if you
had no intent? What would be its automatic definition, right? And that's
what the גמרא's gemara about to discuss. So let's take a look.
דעבינא בה, Da'avinan ba, we ask on this. טעמא דשלא לשמו. Ta'ama
deshelo lishmo. The reason you're חייב chayav is because you specifically
intended for it as a שלמים, shlamim, right? So רש"י Rashi tells
us basically why we ממדייק medayek from the רישא, reisha, סיפא, seifa,
בממדייק bemedayek from the רישא, reisha, but let's just recognize...
Didn't the sage just in general, if it's not the...
Okay, so let's take a look. That's debated, whether a פסח pesach
automatically changes or you have to intentionally change its identity. Okay, so
the גמרא's gemara emphasizing the last statement. טעמא, Ta'ama, the reason it
becomes a שלמים shlamim is שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, you specifically intended
to make it a
non-פסח. pesach. הסתמא, Hastama, if you had no intent, פטור, patur, you
would be exempt, meaning it would be, you'd be exempt from the
transgression because it would be a קרבן פסח, korban pesach, a קרבן
פסח korban pesach brought at the wrong time and therefore invalid sacrifice.
Okay. So the key is that if you have no particular intent,
it still functions as a פסח. pesach. And then it's invalid. ואמאי
פטור? Ve'amai patur? Why are you פטור? patur? פסח בשאר ימות השנה
שלמים הוא. Pesach bishear yemot hashanah shlamim hu. Don't we say that
a פסח pesach during the rest of the year is a שלמים?
shlamim? So even with no intent, it should automatically be a שלמים.
shlamim. שמע מינה, Shma mina, so what we can infer from this
ברייתא braisa is, פסח בשאר ימות השנה בעי עקירה. Pesach bishear yemot
hashanah ba'i akira. That even though it becomes a שלמים shlamim during
the rest of the year, that's only if you uproot its previous
identity. You specifically redesignate it as something else. But it doesn't automatically
become a שלמים. shlamim. ואמר רבי חייא בר גמדא, Ve'amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Gamda, and רבי חייא בר גמדא Rabbi Chiya bar Gamda says,
נזרקה מפי החבורה. Nisdraka mipi hachaburah. This following idea was thrown out
from the community, from the group, meaning from the בית מדרש. Beis
Medrash. ואמרו, Ve'amru, and they said: No, here's how you can explain
why you needed to proactively change its identity. Because normally as Michael
says, we assume its identity is automatically changed. Why here does it
say you have to very directly redefine it? So here's why. הכא
במאי עסקינן, Hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שהיו
בעלים טמאי מתים. kegon shehayu be'alim t'mei meisim. That the reason it
was not brought on the first day, on the fourteenth of Nisan,
was not because it was lost and then found later. The reason
it wasn't brought was because the בעלים be'alim were טמאי מתים. t'mei
meisim. They couldn't bring it. Okay. So therefore what? נידחו לפסח שני.
Nidchu lepesach sheini. Now they're going to bring a פסח שני. pesach
sheini. So what's the relevance of that? What do you think they're
going to bring for the פסח שני? pesach sheini? The same thing
they were going to bring for the פסח ראשון, pesach rishon, this
sheep. Okay. In that case, הסתמא לשמו קאי, hastama lishmo kai, that
this thing is now going to be used for פסח, pesach, and
unless you very consciously change its definition, it's still
considered... Here you're gonna planning on using it and able to use
it next month, so here the definition will only change if you
consciously change it. והאי v'hai this one who דבעי עקירה d'ba'ei akira
you need to you know uproot its name in a very conscious
act. האחר ha'acher another קרבן פסח korban pesach on the rest of
the year לא בעי עקירה lo ba'ei akira you don't have to
uproot its name. Okay, all that was fascinating. What does that have
to do with us? Okay, so here we have this פסח pesach
that you have to consciously change its name blah blah blah. Why
is this relevant for our context? So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says.
So you've got this פסח pesach you're going to use it next
month, it has an identity of a קרבן פסח korban pesach you
שחט shacht it early you שחט shacht it you know sometime between
first פסח Pesach and second פסח Pesach only if you only if
you consciously redefine it is it now a שלמים shlamim but if
you don't consciously redefine it it's a פסח pesach at the wrong
time and it's invalid. So let's see the גמרא's Gemara question. אי
אמרת ei amrat if you say בשלמא bishlama ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד
סוף yeshna lishchita mitchila v'ad sof the שחיטה shechita process starts at
the beginning איפסולי מתחילת שחיטה ipsulei mitchilat shechita so you're שוחט shocheit
it סתם stam from the very minute you begin cutting right you
have now שחט shacht it a פסח pesach at the wrong time
because you have not redefined it you're שוחט shocheit it סתם stam
you שחט shacht it at the wrong time and it's invalid it's
a פסח pesach at the wrong time it's a פסח pesach between
the 14th of ניסן Nissan and the 14th of אייר Iyar that
makes sense. איפסולי מתחילת שחיטה ipsulei mitchilat shechita אלא אי אמרת ela
ei amrat אינה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף eina lishchita ela l'vasof but if
שחיטה shechita is only at the end כיון דשחט בה פורתא keivan
d'shachat bah purta you start שחיטהing shechita it you did not you
were not עוקר oker you were not consciously redefining it you start
שחיטהing shechita it what happens? אידחיי לה מפסח id'chayei lah mi-pesach as
soon as you start cutting into it right this now has a
מום mum you start cutting into the skin it now has a
מום mum can I now bring this as next month? No. Right
next as soon as I start cutting I can't I can't bring
it next month. As soon as I can't bring it next month
right it should automatically be able to say it's a שלמים shlamim
even if I don't consciously redefine it because I've already stopped it
from being able to have a name of a פסח pesach being
able to be brought next month.
Isn't this case? No.
Takes case where it's a פסח pesach that I'm that I could
bring next month if I don't have any intention it's פסול pasul
because it's a פסח pesach brought at the wrong time. Says why
is it a פסח pesach brought at the wrong time? As soon
as you start cutting it's a מום mum and at that second
it can no longer be brought next month. It stops being a
פסח pesach and it's a שלמים shlamim even if I don't have
anything in mind. אי אמרת ei amrat בשלמא bishlama if you say
the שחיטה shechita process starts at the beginning then as soon as
I start cutting what have I done? I've done a שחיטה shechita
of a פסח pesach it's already defined as a שחיטה shechita of
a פסח pesach at the wrong time it's פסול pasul but if
as when I start cutting I haven't done a שחיטה shechita yet
right so I've just cut it I've just made a מום mum
so when I finally get around to making a שחיטה shechita it's
no longer fit for being
any קרבן korban you can never bring any קרבן korban because when
I start cutting it if there's no שחיטה shechita until the end
I made a מום mum in it.
So that is of course an excellent question right because what Michael
is saying is and it really goes back to the very first
day's. How could you say the whole שחיטה shechita is only at
the end? By the time you get there it's a טריפה treifa
and if you want to apply it to a קרבן korban by
the time you get there it has it's a בעל מום. ba'al
mum. Right so somehow we have to you're right so it's very
bizarre we have to sort of bracket that. Yes yes yes but
that's all part of the process of getting to the שחיטה shechita
so somehow it's not a problem. But once you say that how
can we pay now all of a sudden pay attention to that
to talk about redefining? Oh but at least we could still say
although it doesn't invalidate the שחיטה shechita and invalidate the קרבן korban
it should at least tell me though that it's not fit for
using next month. It is a splitting of hairs. I you're absolutely
correct. I don't have a good explanation for that. So let's see
at least what the גמרא Gemara does with this answer. אלא so
but אי אמרת ei amrat אינה שחיטה אלא לבסוף eina shechita ela
l'vasof כיון דשחט בה פורתא keivan d'shachat bah purta when you begin
שחיטהing shechita אידחיי לה מפסח id'chayei lah mi-pesach it can no longer
be used for פסח pesach next month and therefore you don't have
to you shouldn't have to redefine it. It automatically is redefined. אידך
כי קשחט שלמים קשחט idach ki kashachat shlamim kashachat so when you
continue שחיטהing shechita it's no longer a פסח pesach it's a שלמים
shlamim because it can already not be used for next month. So
אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye so Abaye said מה meh no.
נהי
דאידחיי לה מפסח nehi d'id'chayei lah mi-pesach it's true that even when
you begin שחיטהing shechita you can no longer use it for a
פסח pesach next month. בדמי פסח מי אידחיי bidmei pesach mi id'chayei
it's not out of the category of פסח pesach altogether because you
could still redeem it, transfer the money and use the money for
a פסח pesach next month. So it has not completely been redefined
just because you started cutting it.
Right when can you redeem it?
You start cutting. So he says oh there's a מום mum it
can't be a פסח. pesach. No maybe if I were to stop
at this second I could transfer the קדושה kedusha to money and
use the money for a פסח. pesach. Okay so it's not yet
totally out of the category.
וכי תימא בי העמדה והערכה v'chi teima bei ha'amada v'haaracha one minute
in order to redeem an animal it's based on a verse in
the תורה Torah where it says that you should stand the animal
before the כהן kohen and you should estimate the value and from
there we learn that you can only redeem it if it's still
alive not if it's already dead. So here so
that doesn't bother me Abaye says it's not dead yet just because
you started שחיטהing. shechita אפילו הכי והתנן afilu hachi v'hatnan we taught
in the משנה Mishnah שחט בה שנים או רוב שנים shachat bah
shnayim o rov shnayim ועדיין היא מפרכסת v'adayin hi mefarchesset right very
interesting we referred to this yesterday and we've mentioned this a couple
of times once you
So even if you started שחטינג, shechting, you can still redeem it
because it's still technically as alive, and since the money could still
go to הקדש, hekdesh, it's not yet completely out of the category.
So and with that actually we end this whole fascinating discussion of
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshna l'shchita mitchila v'ad sof. I have
to agree with Michael, which is not only is this immediate application
frustrating, but the whole discussion is frustrating for two reasons. Number one
conceptually, right, it's like what are you trying to define? If you're
trying to define the process, it would seem that everybody should agree
that the process begins from the beginning. You're in the middle of
the process of שחיטה. shchita. If you want to define when is
the process over, or when have you completed, you know, or what
and when is the act of, right? So that would seem that
that's at the end. Even if you somehow, so number one, what
are we trying to define so that give me a definition that
I can understand, you know, where these two sides are really debating.
The process seems to begin at the beginning and seems to, you
know, so you're involved in the process. So now maybe the question
is: does that matter? Does it matter for הלכה halachic purposes? That's
maybe a way of framing it to say that I'm doing the
act of שחיטה shchita or as long as I haven't finished, being
involved in the process is insignificant. So maybe that's one way of
framing it, but it still is a problem because if so far
you don't recognize that I'm doing something yet, why haven't I made
it a טרפה? treifa? Why haven't I made it a בעל מום
ba'al mum by the time I get to the end? So those
are, I think, very, you know, good questions which the גמרא Gemara
completely jumps over. And I also agree with Michael, the fact that
here all of a sudden we're saying, "Oh, you've made it a
בעל מום, ba'al mum, it's no longer a פסח ראשון," Pesach Rishon,
to say that every case I've made the קרבן korban a בעל
מום. ba'al mum. You know, so how come all of a sudden
though there I'm able to bracket? Well, that's part of every שחיטה.
shchita. But when it somehow it has a different implication, like changing
its identity from a פסח Pesach to a שלמים, shlamim, then I'm
no longer going to bracket it. So anyway, very interesting question about
thinking about process and the גמרא Gemara passes it in applies it
in a number of other סוגיות sugyot about how we think about
the process of שחיטה, shchita, but always a little frustrating, hard to
precisely conceptually.
This is only case where there really is a נפקא מינא? nafka
mina?
No, the גמרא Gemara applies it elsewhere other נפקא מינא. nafka minas.
No, the גמרא Gemara applies it elsewhere, like let's say I'll just
give you one other example, right, I'm שחטינג shechting an animal to
on, I forget, I forget exactly the case but somehow if you
started like right before שבת Shabbat ends and you finish?
Yeah, no, no, but I'm like שחטינג shechting it לעבודה זרה, l'avoda
zara, so therefore, you know, at what stage does the animal already
become איסור הנאה? issur hana'ah? The beginning of the process or at
the end of the process? So, you know, there's other places where
the גמרא Gemara applies it.
You're like thinking about it on שבת, Shabbat, right? If I start,
if I start something
before
שבת Shabbat and it finishes,
yeah, but that's also a שבת Shabbat question, like if I start
cooking something before שבת Shabbat and it finishes cooking, that's not limited
to, that is an interesting question, but it also has to do
with specific שבת Shabbat issues. Okay, let's, yes.
Why isn't there a simple... What? Why isn't there a simple...
Well, that's a simple answer? Yeah, that's what I want to know.
Yeah, that the process is successfully completed.
Right, well that we did say, everybody needs it to successfully complete,
right?
And it's one whole
process in which case you retroactively go back and say it being
part of a process and have whatever implications there are. And in
the event that it's not successfully completed, then you approach it with
granularity.
Right, so well the גמרא Gemara says, well I would say like
this, the גמרא Gemara says exactly that, when it we're only talking
when it was successfully completed and then we can go back and
talk about the beginning. When it's not successful then the גמרא Gemara
says that, you know, then then also no debate then you were
doing nothing at the beginning because now retroactively we see that we
were doing nothing. But when it was successfully completed, you know, that
was that was my question as well. If my question is, you
know, what's the when does the process begin, the process begins at
the beginning assuming it was successfully completed. If the question is when
is the process over, right, that's at the end. So what exactly
is your question, you know? So the only way I can sort
of frame the question is: okay, I admit that right now you're
doing the process of שחיטה, shchita, which is why you haven't made
it a טרפה treifa or בעל מום, ba'al mum, because you're doing
the process of שחיטה, shchita, but I just don't think that the
process of שחיטה shchita is enough to be a problem or be
significant for certain הלכות halachot that say that require the act of
שחיטה. shchita. So if the question is, have you transgressed שחטינג shechting
something outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the process of שחיטה shchita
is not enough. You need to do the full שחיטה. shchita. If
the issue is what was the other נפקא מינא nafka mina we
had here? פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. Now again the גמרא Gemara reject,
well actually that's not good because there, there that should have been
clear, right? By the פרה אדומה Para Aduma if it's the process
everybody should agree the process begins at the beginning. So that's why
I said I really don't understand the debate. It seems very clear
that the process, you know, is defined from the beginning. So alright
and you know even not only intuitively but from the fact that
it's not considered a טרפה treifa by the time you get to
the end. Alright, so let's go on now. That is all we
have for this for now. I apologize for the lack of precision
in understanding the two sides. Let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. Now we go on to
a different הלכה. halacha. השוחט בשניים ובשלושה מקומות שחיטתו כשרה. Hashochet b'shnayim
uvishlosha mekomot shchitato keshera. You know, even not only intuitively, but from
the fact that it's not considered a טריפה treifa by the time
you get to the end. All right, so let's go on now.
That is all we have for this for now. I apologize for
the lack of precision in understanding the two sides. Let's take a
look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. Now
we go on to a different הלכה. halakha. השוחט בשנים ובשלשה מקומות
שחיטתו כשרה. Hashochet b'shnayim u-v'shlosha mekomot shechitatu kesheira. If he slaughtered
in two or three different places, it's valid. Now what does that
mean? So I'm going to give you what not what רש"י's Rashi
explanation, well, okay, I'll first start with the simple explanation. It means
imagine that this is, here maybe this is a bit better, this
is your סימן, siman, right? You need רוב, rov, but let's say
you do 40 percent here, then you start down here and you
do 20 percent here, right? Or like 20 percent there. So they
don't make a complete circle, but if you combine the amount that
each one has cut in, you've got the majority.
And you did it all without שהייה? shehiya?
Yeah, and you somehow did that all without שהייה, shehiya, okay? So
that's the question. Is that valid, or do you need the רוב
rov to all be in one place? Even though assuming here they're
all in the same circle, it's not like part here, part up
here, part down here, right? But they're but they're not all continuous.
Okay, what's the הלכה? halakha? So he says it's valid. כי אמריתה
קמיה דשמואל, Ki amritah kameih de-Shmuel, when it's said in front of
שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי, amar lei, no, that's not good, בעינן שחיטה
מפורעת וליכא. beinan shechita meforaat ve-leika. You need an exposed שחיטה shechita
and you don't have it. Meaning you need it to be a
straight cut so that you know you can basically like, you know
we heard yesterday, like you know bend the סימן siman and see
the entire cut straight.
By the way, whatever the rule here
happens to be, we'd probably say is no. Well obviously, and who's
gonna have has the expertise to do a crazy case like this
anyway? Okay, ואף ריש לקיש סבר בעינן שחיטה מפורעת. Ve-af Reish Lakish
savar beinan shechita meforaat. Even ריש לקיש Reish Lakish holds you need
that. דאמר ריש לקיש, D'amar Reish Lakish, מניין לשחיטה שהיא מפורעת? minayin
l'shechita she-hi meforaat? How do you know שחיטה shechita has to be
like, you know, exposed? שנאמר חץ שחוט לשונם מרמה דיבר. shene'emar chetz
shachut leshonam mirma diber. There there
there tongue is like a cutting arrow when they speak, you know,
guile or they speak a treachery. So you see that the same
way what an arrow cuts, right, it slices straight, it doesn't, you
know, do this weird thing, so it has to be like the
cutting of an arrow straight. Okay. איתיביה רבי אלעזר. Eitiveih Rabbi Elazar.
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar asked: בשנים אוחזים בסכין ושוחטים. B'shnayim ochazim b'sakin
v'shochtim. Two, we have a משנה mishna coming up that says two
people are holding onto two sides of a knife. Okay, now actually
we're originally going to understand that it means two people are holding
onto two different knives and each one is שוחט-ing. shochet So that
would be a way you could do this, right? One guy's got
it from the front, one guy's got it from the side, each
guy does 40 percent or 30 percent. Okay, and let's see what
the משנה mishna says. Two people are holding knives, here it's reading
it as knives in the plural,
ושוחטים, v'shochtim, אפילו אחד מלמעלה ואחד מלמטה שחיטה כשרה. afilu echad milma'ala
v'echad milmata shechita kesheira. Even if one is from the front and
one is from the back, it's valid. So you see that's exactly
this case, the שחיטה's shechita in two different places.
אמאי? Amai? Why is that true? והליכא שחיטה מפורעת? V'ha-leika shechita meforaat?
You don't have an exposed שחיטה? shechita? אמר ליה רבי ירמיה, Amar
lei Rabbi Yirmiyah, משנתנו בסכין אחד ושני בני אדם. mishnateinu b'sakin echad
u-shnei bnei adam. Our משנה mishna is not talking about two two
knives, it's talking about two people but one knife. So what's the
case with one knife? Here you've got your neck, Michael is holding
the two handles, hold the handle Michael. Michael's holding the handle here,
I'm holding the handle here, and we're שוחט-ing shochet like this, we're
sort of שוחט-ing, shochet you know, like if you so you imagine
both holding it now obviously there's a problem because although we're both
holding a handle we're supposed to be doing this, if you're two
people are holding a handle it's more likely you're going to push
down, right, than you're going to do a back and forth motion.
You can view
it as like a saw.
Like it's like a saw, right, like a two-handled saw. Okay, so
that is the case. Not two separate knives but two separate handles
on one knife and it's a sawing it's like a saw.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, if אמר
ליה רבי אבא, amar lei Rabbi Abba, אי הכי, ei hachi, if
that's true, היינו דתניא עלה, hainu d'tanya alah, what about what we
taught on it: אין חוששים שמא ידרוסו זה על זה. ein chosheshim
shema yidresu zeh al zeh. We're not afraid that each person will
make it a טריפה. treifa. How does that make sense? אי אמרת
בשלמא בשתי סכינים ובשני בני אדם, Ei amrat bishlama bishtei sakin u-vishnei
bnei adam, like we thought, two people with two knives at separate
places in the סימן, siman, שפיר, shapir, I understand what what my
concern might be טריפה. treifa. What was me my concern? מהו דתימא
ליחוש דמסתמכי אהדדי, Mah d'teima lichosh d'mistamchi ahadadi, each one will rely
on the other one, right? That's always a problem with distributed responsibility.
So if Michael is שוחט-ing shochet in one place and I'm שוחט-ing
shochet in the other, I figure eh Michael will do the רוב,
rov, I don't really have to worry. והאי לא אתי למעבד רובא
והאי לא אתי למעבד רובא. Ve-hai lo ati le-mabad ruba ve-hai lo
ati le-mabad ruba. Neither one will do the רוב, rov, or according
to some תוספות Tosafot says even combined we won't do the רוב,
rov, so we'll leave it as a טריפה. treifa. קמשמע לן דאין
חוששין, Kamashma lan d'ein chosheshin, you're not afraid of that. אלא אי
אמרת בסכין אחד ושני בני אדם, Ela ei amrat b'sakin echad u-shnei
bnei adam, but if it's the concern about two people holding two
handles of a knife, like like a saw, היי אין חוששין שמא
יטרפו זה על זה, hai ein chosheshin shema yitrefu zeh al zeh,
the concern is not that they won't make it a טריפה, treifa,
right, what's a טריפה? treifa? טריפה Treifa is like a hole without
it being complete, right, without being a good שחיטה? shechita? אבל שמא
ידרסו זה על זה מבעי ליה? aval shema yidresu zeh al zeh
mibaya lei? The concern would be that we would put pressure on
the knife, right? If you're both holding two handles, you might do
a sawing motion, but it's also very easy to just do a
pushing motion, right? So if the if that were the scenario, it
should have said that that was the concern and it doesn't. אמר
ליה רבי אבא, Amar lei Rabbi Abba, to אמר ליה רבי אבין,
Amar lei Rabbi Abin, okay, תני אין חוששים
שמא ידרסו זה על זה.
tani ein
chosheshim
shema yidresu zeh al zeh.
So you've got a problem, just take out your eraser, change the
text. Okay, but yes, the scenario is two people with one knife,
but two separate knives, right? That might be a different story because
again this is the question of can you have a cut that's
not all right there? continuous. It's, well, this opinion is saying it's
fine, we have not concluded. Okay, מתיב רבי אבין, Mativ Reb Avin,
so Rabbi Avin asked, שחט את הושט למטה ואת הקנה למעלה, Shachat
et ha-veshet lemata ve-et ha-kanah lemala, let's say you shechted the ושט
veshet below and the קנה kanah above, right, I mean one way
to think about this is you're going at an angle, so you
shechted the ושט veshet and you know, then the קנה, kanah, so
the cut of the קנה kanah is higher than the ושט veshet
because you're at an angle, or you could imagine that you moved
your hand, right, your hand cut through one and then it jumped
a little, right, and then you finished higher or lower than you
were starting. או את הקנה למעלה או את הושט למעלה ואת הקנה
למטה, O et ha-kanah lemala, o et ha-veshet lemala ve-et ha-kanah lemata,
or the reverse, the ושט veshet above and the קנה kanah below,
שחיטתו כשירה, shechitato kesherah, it's valid. So now we're talking about not
one cut with one סימן, siman, but we are talking about two
separate cuts with two סימנים, simanim, but it's not exposed, right, if
you cut open the בית השחיטה, beit ha-shechitah, you're not going to
see a continuous cut, you don't have one cut that exposes everything.
ואמאי, Ve-amai, why is that valid? והליכא שחיטה מפורעת, Ve-leika shechitah mefura'at,
so you don't have an exposed שחיטה. shechitah. הוא מותיב לה והוא
מפרק לה, Hu motiv lah ve-hu mifarek lah, he asked the question
and he answered it, בשחיטה דסיכי דקומסא, bi-shechitah de-siki de-kumsa, it's like
a, it's like a quill. So if you think about the edge
of a quill, right, the edge of a quill is like is,
you know, is a straight angle, right? Anybody ever see what, you
know, like the edge of a quill, right? It looks like it's
flat on the top and angled like that at like that. So
the basic point is we're not saying you cut, your hand jerked,
and then you did that, then it would not be one exposed
cut. We're saying you cut at an angle. So if you cut
at an angle, it's true, it's not perpendicular, but it is one
exposed cut and you can open it and see the whole cut.
So that's why that would be okay. So again, the question is
if you cut the right things you're supposed to cut but it's
not in one continuous line so it's not one exposed thing, is
that okay or not?
But it's still a continuous line, it's just at an angle.
That's the answer. The answer is it's an angle. Don't think it
means you cut, your hand jerked, and then you did it in
a different place.
Right, but so this doesn't answer
the question of whether if you cut and your hand jerked.
Right, so that's what's being debated. Right, we know that an angle's
okay, but what if it's really in two separate locations? Okay. So,
okay. ההוא תורא דאישחט בשנים ושלשה מקומות, Hahu tura de-ishchat bi-shnayim u-shloshah
mekomot, now we're going to have a story about this.
There was a cow that was shechted just like this, two or
three places, assuming like we're talking about that it means like, you
know, different places, you know, the front of the סימן, siman, the
side of the סימן siman and so on, not different heights necessarily,
but different places within one line of the סימן. siman. Okay, so,
אתו לקמיה דרב יוסף בר שמואל בר מרתא, atu le-kamei de-Rav Yosef
bar Shmuel bar Marta, so רב יוסף בר שמואל בר מרתא Rav
Yosef bar Shmuel bar Marta came,
presumably people had some questions about whether it was kosher or not,
שקיל משופרי שופרי, shakil mi-shufrei shufrei, he took
the best of the meat. He said, you got any problems? No
problem. Send the meat over to me, I'll take care of it.
I know some of you with some of this stuff about the
single malt whiskey, you know, was coming up or whatever, somebody who
lives in Lower East Side and lives near to רב דוד פיינשטיין
Rav David Feinstein was asking him about it, he said, you got
any problems? I'll take it.
So you got any questions? Fine, just bring it to me. All
right. So אמר ליה רב זירא, Amar leih Rav Zeira, so רב
זירא Rav Zeira said, למדתנו רבנו, limadatenu rabbeinu,
so from your actions we have, we can infer that משנתנו בשני
סכינים ובשני
בני אדם, mishnatenu bi-shnei sakinim u-vi-shnei bnei adam, that the משנה mishnah
that said two people shechting would be even two knives, even two
knives in different locations. Okay, because you're saying now that you don't,
that that is good. So the משנה mishnah would be referring to
even to that case. Okay, and with that, so אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, okay,
so with that we basically end that discussion and it sounds like
the ruling is that it's okay, that you do not need a
straight cut exposed, even if your hand were to jerk up or
jerk down or even if it would be in two separate locations
on the סימן. siman. But I should say that there's a debate
in the ראשונים rishonim of exactly how to understand this scenario, I
only gave you one scenario. There's also a debate how we rule,
but it sounds like the גמרא Gemara is ruling very leniently on
this. It's impossible
though, I mean, and you know, the דין din may be based
on yesterday. Yeah, I mean practically it never happens anyway, it would,
it would require real expertise to get this to happen.
Okay, so what it, what it sounds like is that we're really
concerned with the act of שחיטה. shechitah. Yes, from the standpoint of
the, of the animal. Uh-huh. Here, as opposed to someone having had
completed שחיטה, shechitah,
you
mean because the act, oh because of the whole idea of two
people and that the act isn't an integrated act? It's more object-oriented
than the process, one process of שחיטה. shechitah. That is a good
point too. Having two people doing it and combining, right, makes it
that it's not, that it's not one person
process-oriented, it's also almost, although there really can't be שהייה shehiyah between
the two halves, so to some degree you could conceptually say, right,
if I do it and then Michael finishes it with no שהייה,
shehiyah, it's still good.
So they gave me a case where there's no
שהייה.
shehiyah. Right, so since there's no שהייה, shehiyah, you could say that
our act becomes integrated into one act. But you are right, it
does, it is more, this discussion is definitely more object-focused than act
or process-focused. That's correct. Let's just try to finish up to the
משנה. mishnah. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, החליד את הסכין בין סימן לסימן ופסקו פסולה. hechlid et ha-sakin
bein siman le-siman u-fesako pesulah. So if you, this is the problem.
Let's just try to finish up to the משנה, Mishnah, okay? Okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: החליד את
הסכין בין סימן לסימן ופסקו פסולה. Hechlid et ha-sakin bein siman le-siman
u-pesako pesula. So if you, this is the פסולה pesula of חלדה
chalada of burrowing, you stuck the knife right in between the two
סימנים simanim and then you did the cutting, it's invalid. The cutting
has to be from the outside in, you can't start on the
inside and work your way out.
תחת העור כשרה. Tachat ha-or keshera.
What does he mean by ופסקו? u-pesako?
Then you cut the סימן. siman. Okay, so you stuck it in
the middle of the two סימנים. simanim. You didn't cut straight like
that, you stuck it in the middle and then you worked your
way out. That's חלדה, chalada, that's burrowing in between.
ופסקו U-pesako is cut-cut.
Right. Okay. תחת העור, Tachat ha-or, however, if you stuck your knife
under the two סימנים simanim but between the סימנים simanim and the
skin, so you didn't cut the skin on the outside. You stuck
it between the סימן siman but you still cut the סימנים simanim
in the normal motion. You punctured the skin and then did the
שחיטה. shechita. That's valid. That's not חלדה chalada because you're only starting
under the skin, not between the
סימנים. simanim. מאי קמ''ל? Mai kamashmalan? What are you teaching me? תנינא,
Tanina, we taught it. או שהחליד את הסכין תחת השני ופסקה. O
she-hechlid et ha-sakin tachat ha-sheni u-pesakah. It says that if you stuck
the knife under the second סימן siman and you cut it. רבי
ישבב אומר נבילה, Rabbi Yeshevav omer neveila, it's a נבילה. neveila. רבי
עקיבא אומר טרפה, Rabbi Akiva omer tereifa, it's a טרפה. tereifa. We
won't worry about why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva calls it a טרפה,
tereifa, we'll discuss that later. But anyway, you see that here if
you stick your knife in the middle, you make it a חלדה.
chalada. It's talking about you did the first סימן siman correctly, okay?
You שחט-ed shacht the first סימן siman correctly. Then you stuck your
knife above the second סימן siman and cut it down. You see
what you did? So you did the first שחיטה shechita like this,
but then before you got to the second סימן, siman, you went
above the second סימן siman and you cut in the down motion.
So גמרא Gemara says that is not necessarily the same case. אי
ממתניתין, Ei mi-matnitin, if we just told me that was חלדה, chalada,
הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought הני מילי מלמטה למעלה,
hani mili mi-lemata le-ma'ala, דלא קעביד דרך שחיטה. delo ka-avid derech shechita.
You're going in the wrong order, right? You're sticking your knife between
the second סימן siman and the spinal cord and you're moving down.
The normal movement is towards the spinal cord. Here you're burrowing on
top and moving away from the spinal cord. That maybe is the
problem of burrowing because you're going in the wrong order. אבל מלמעלה
למטה, Aval mi-lema'ala le-mata, דקעביד דרך שחיטה, deka-avid derech shechita, but if
you're going towards the spinal cord which is the normal order, אימא
שפיר דמי, eima shapir dami, maybe it's good even if you start
in the middle of the two, right? So in our case you
start in the middle of the two and you go towards the
spinal cord. So you're going in the right direction, you're just starting
in the middle. And then you maybe took your knife out and
did the first one. So maybe that's okay as long as you're
doing the right direction. קמ''ל Kamashmalan that it's not. Okay.
Now let me hold on a minute. תחת העור כשרה. Tachat ha-or
keshera. And then we did say that if you just start in
the skin it's okay if you didn't start from the full outside.
בי רב אמר תחת העור איני יודע. Bei Rav amar tachat ha-or
eini yodeia. I don't know what the story is if you start
under the skin. Maybe it's good, maybe it's not. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya
lehu, and they asked one final question. לבי רב דאמר תחת העור
איני יודע, Le-bei Rav de-amar tachat ha-or eini yodeia, starting puncturing the
skin is not good if you didn't start from the full outside,
how about the following two cases? תחת המטלית מהו? Tachat ha-matlit mahu?
Let's say you had a cloth around the neck of the פרה,
parah, of the cow
and you started under the cloth. So it's not even a part
of the cow. How much does he say you have to fully
start on the outside? What for him is considered burrowing? If even
in the skin before you get to the סימנים simanim is burrowing,
maybe if you have a cloth around the neck and you start
under the cloth maybe that's not good.
או תחת צמר מסובך מהו? O tachat tzemer mesubach mahu? תיקו. Teiku.
What if it's a sheep and it's got all of its wool
here and you start with the knife in the wool? So at
least that's a little better, it's part of it, but it's not
even the skin. Would that be considered burrowing? תיקו. Teiku. So I'm
not going to read the last line because the last line actually
is a fascinating discussion I want to leave till tomorrow. But let
me just summarize the last thing we just said. There's a פסול
psul of חלדה, chalada, burrowing, which as we heard yesterday is why
the front of the knife is flat so you can't pierce through
the middle. You have to start with the edge and move out.
So what is that פסול psul of burrowing? One case is you
start on top of the second סימן siman and you move your
way down in the opposite direction. That's clearly no good. But what
if you start in the then we ask if starting in the
middle even if you go in the right direction, if you're starting
between the סימנים simanim and going in the right and then let's
say you come out and do the other one, that's also no
good. That's חלדה, chalada, that's no good. The question is if you're
doing everything, you're starting in the right order, you're starting you're going
up between the two, you're going in the right direction, you're doing
one and then two straight, the only thing is you didn't start
outside of the neck. You started between the סימן siman and the
skin or you started outside the neck but not totally exposed under
a piece of cloth or in the wool of the sheep. Is
even that burrowing? That seems a little extreme, but there is an
opinion that it might be and the גמרא Gemara leaves that undecided
whether according to that opinion according to רב Rav whether it is
or not. Okay, so we will pick up here with the last
line.